welcome to another video or in this video we will discuss about the network layer so this is the top if you counting from the bottom of the layer it will be the third layer so if you counting the top to bottom it will be in the fifth layer right.
So, this is one of the important layer this source IP and destination IP will be added in this layer that's called as a network layer so let's see how the network layer will be the open principle of the network layer.
So, the main open principle is like there are two things one is a source IP and the destination IP will be added in each of your packets which was sending right.
In a transport layer we have a lot of segments we already seen there's a lot of packets we have so we need to route this packet we need to send this packet to the target server.
So, here is our machine and we need to send it to the Google server so from here and we need to take the result from our Google server to our machine.
So, we need to add our two things are in there so one is a source IP and another one is a destination IP.
So, source IP is your IP and because you are when you are querying something to your friend so you are you are giving the source IP as well as a destination IP right we are giving both of the address.
So, big up because if T yeah let's let's say let's continue here you are giving two address your address and your friend address right.
So, the similar way we are giving our address and the destination address to all the packets which we are sending ok.
So, our IP is like it's like 192 or something ok this is our IP and the destination IP there was a Google IP so just we can get the Google IP.
So, one 42 to 50 or 91 140 it's a Google IP 142 dot 250 right so this is a Google IP we need to add both the things in every packets ok.
So, this is the Oking principle of a network layer the most important thing we will there is a lot of things will be in the network layer but in cyber security so what we need.
So, these are the few concepts we need or important concepts we need so we are discussing that concepts in this course it's not a professional networking course to explain each and everything in the protocols and in the background process of every layer so but we need it.
It's enough for us we need only a few things from the voice model so that's where we are covering we are covering this match ok so this both things will be added in the every every packets ok so next thing there's a data link layer ok.
Let's break this and before that we will discuss a few more things in the IP addressing in the network layer ok so I already said there is a source IP and the destination IP will be added here and so there is a two IP address owners of private IP.
And another one is a public IP we have two IP's one is a private and another one is a public IP so the private IP is like it was provided by your router so let's explain this mechanism so here you have your own home router so in the inside the home router there's a lot of machine that was connected with your router the mobile phone PC computers and TV ok.
TV tablets a lot of devices are connected so this modem will modem router will give the private IP to its like 192.168.18.1 ok so if you if you take the command prompt and if you do the IP config slash all so here you can see this is a default gateway.
Of the of the network this is a default gateway of the network so my router IP will be like 192.168.18.1 right so every packets every packets from my machines so every packets in my each of the machine this machine this machine it will first reaches to the default gate this is the gateway right so this is the gateway between our computer and our Google server.
Right or any other server right so this is the gateway so we will.
This is the IP address of the of my router and the router will assign IP address ok to every machine by using some dck protocol.
18.3 18.4 18.5 there is lot of machines will be connected inside the network so every demo the router will assign private IP to every device shared the network by using the dck protocol we will discuss this protocol later ok.
So if you need to communicate or if you need to send high to this computer to this mobile phone you can use a private IP ok.
So you can use a private IP for a communication ok so if you if you need to send anything inside your boundary inside your network you can use your own private private IP which will be given by the router or a modem ok router or a modem.
You can use this you use this private IP to communicate inside what communicate inside your network ok.
So but if you need to communicate outside of the network this private IP will not work because you need to are going to you are going to your packet will be going to this and then it will be router to your Google server right.
So this private IP will not work here ok so we have a that way we have a public IP ok so let's I am not going to show my IP in a public I will show my.
No problem let's I will show my IP if I going to Google and I'm searching what's my IP so you can see here this my public IP this was provided by the service provider ok so the public IP was provided by the service provider.
So who is a service provider so like our air tell our BSNL. So even network providers ok our order phone so air the service provider will give you the public IP that's where they are.
You are paying some amount to amount every month to your service provider ok so for this IP ok.
And if you need to communicate outside to outside in your network so let's go for let's go to the public IP if you want to communicate let's say there is a modem and there's few devices inside your network and this device ok this device needs to communicate to the.
Google server which was not which was not in your network it's outside of the network what's the inside of the so whatever machines connected under the router or modem it's inside of the network and other machines are outside of the network ok so you can't able to communicate by using the private IP the private IP you can use in a.
Instead of the network so if you want to communicate outside so you need a public IP so this computer have a private IP of 18.2 let's take an example this needs to communicate with the on 42 to 50 the Google server so the packets will be first send to this ok ok the packets will be first send to this and the more router convert that private IP into the public IP and it will reach it to the.
OK from here to here your packet will be like it's like on 98.2 and from modem it will convert your.
Pack it with the public IP ok so it will it will add your public IP 58.15.85 something ok so it will convert your private IP into the public IP by using one of the.
So we like not ok network address transaction so the network address transaction is like it the main purpose of network address transaction is it will convert your private IP.
Into the public IP ok.
So the main purpose it will change your private IP into the public IP so you can easily communicate with the Google server ok so this the.
Or all brief of the private IP and the public IP so it will be added and the network layer right. So in the private IP let's go for one more review in the private IP you can use only the private IP for.
Or instead of the network communication but if you want to communicate outside of the network you need a public IP so the public IP has been provided by the service provider like at a lot of.
So they will give us separate IP to you and by using the using that IP you can communicate outside of the network ok so this is the overall explanation of the network layer ok.
And let's hope of this video and continue in the next video, see you guys.